Okay
בוקר טוב Boker Tov everybody.
Today's דף daf is ס"ז Samech Zayin and we started a פרק.
perek. So we begin with the very last line on ס"ו עמוד
ב' Samech Vav Amud Bet and there is a radical change of
topic, not that radical we're still in the world of נדרים, Nedarim,
but nevertheless you know we've sort of been dealing with of course
what is the scope of a נדר neder and then we've been
dealing with התרה Hatarah although it should be mentioned at this stage
that even though this התרה Hatarah discussion has sort of like weaved
in and out over the last פרק perek in particular which was
really devoted to התרה, Hatarah, but התרה Hatarah sort of came up
indirectly in other places but there was never a sort of direct
statement of like where do you get this idea that you can
do התרת נדרים? Hataras Nedarim? Right? אמאי? amai? You know so how
do you learn out that you need a בית דין Beis Din
or can one person do it or whatever? Like there was never
like a straight discussion of it. So without that although we've discussed
a lot of course about it, we turn to this פרק perek
which is about the what is explicit in the תורה Torah which
is the phenomenon of הפרה. Hafarah. The הפרה Hafarah is annulment and
again I don't know התרה Hatarah if you want is releasing and
הפרה Hafarah is annulment or voiding maybe or something. And the תורה
Torah says that basically in the context of a married woman that
her husband can go ahead and void make her void her vows.
And the one basic difference you have oh let me just say
two or three basic הלכות halachos and then we'll look at the
גמרא. Gemara. Okay number one is I mean the question about like
oh excuse me her married woman her husband can and an unmarried
woman her father can. Okay. So because he senses that a woman
is always under the control of some man. The exception being if
she's an adult and divorced and widowed, she's left her father's home
she's gone what does a woman do when she leaves her father's
home? If the woman never gets married it's somehow conceptually assumed that
she's always in her father's home. And another point to be made
is that while in later
הלכה halacha or in the גמרא Gemara you know in the rabbinic
understanding when a girl is a בוגרת bogeres the ripe old age
of twelve and a half she is conceptually not in her father's
home and she's independent, in the תורה Torah you don't have that
idea of an independent woman. Okay. She basically if she would never
get married then she'd be whether physically she's in her father's home
conceptually she's in her father's home. So she goes from her father's
home to her husband's home. Okay. If then her husband dies or
divorces her then she's left her father's home left her husband's home
that's when she's independent. And that's when the תורה Torah says ונדר
אלמנה וגרושה כל אשר אסרה על נפשה יקום עליה. v'neder almanah u'grushah
kol asher asrah al nafshah yakum aleha. Okay. כל אשר אסרה על
נפשה יקום
עליה.
kol asher asrah al nafshah
yakum aleha. That
that's the one woman who's not under any man's control. But if
she's in her father's home her father annuls it, if she's in
her husband's home her husband annuls it, that's the institution of הפרה.
Hafarah. Now the תורה Torah also says that the husband hears it
ביום שמעו, b'yom sham'o,
if he annuls it on the day that he hears it. So
we only have that day to annul. The תורה Torah also refers
to a phenomenon of הקם יקימנו. Hakem yakimenu. If he established it.
So there's passive if you don't respond on the day we'll see
what the day means twenty-four hours till nightfall or whatever you don't
respond on the day then you've lost your opportunity, you the husband
or whatever the father we'll talk about the father. Okay. Then there's
also the active is to say I'm good with that, good נדר,
neder, I'm making it, there's an act of הקמה. hakamah. Okay. So
number one if a father can annul or the husband can annul
unless she's independent. Number two is that it has to be done
on the day and there's this opposite thing called הקמה hakamah which
obviously voids any possibility of doing הפרה Hafarah even later on that
same day. The third point to make is that the difference between
הפרה Hafarah and התרה Hatarah is that הפרה Hafarah is basically מכאן
ולהבא. me'kan u'laba.
התרה Hatarah is retroactive. So if a woman makes a נדר neder
and she violates it and then her husband hears it and then
he's מיפר meifer it, she has still transgressed what she has done
until that point. Okay. הפרה Hafarah is different. הפרה Hafarah doesn't say
you deep down you wouldn't have really meant it, remember התרה Hatarah
is based on a model of טעות, to'os, so if it was
really a טעות to'os then it was never binding. So that's why
it works retroactively. Whereas הפרה Hafarah is based on the power of
the husband or the power of the father. Hey I'm in control
right you know you can't go ahead and make a commitment right
without you know if it gets in the way oh like you
know right I don't care that you promised something to your friends
or whatever you have to get my permission right so you know
so that's sort of the idea that it's because they have such
control they have the right to say no I'm voiding it. But
it's a voiding that basically works מכאן ולהבא me'kan u'laba and not
retroactively. So those are the basic concepts of הפרה. Hafarah.
Yeah Dave did you have a question? Question: What if she's at
twelve and a half and her father has passed away and she's
not married?
After twelve and a half? Even if her father didn't pass away,
according to the- oh you mean according to the תורה? Torah? Yeah
in according to the תורה Torah that's true, a girl who is
a- who is a- you know who's a יתומה, yasoma, an orphan,
right, would probably also be independent. But according to the גמרא, Gemara,
it doesn't matter. Once she's twelve and a half she's in the
תורה, Torah,
there's no space between father's house and husband's house. Because there's no
age limit in the תורה. Torah. It's basically she's in her father's
house, however old she is until she's in her husband's house. You're
right, if she were an orphan, then she would be independent. But
in the- but in the גמרא, Gemara, right, and חז"ל, Chazal, you
have that actual independent space, that big gap that opens up, it's
a big gap, right, especially if the society has moved beyond קידושי
קטנה kiddushey ktanah as a common phenomenon, you have this big gap
from the age of twelve and a half until she gets married
where she's independent, right?
Any other
question? התרה, hatara, הנערה, hanara, הקמה, hakama, and then what is הפרה?
hafara?
הפרה hafara is- התרה hatara is what the בית דין Beis Din
does, it's a retroactive releasing. הפרה hafara is what the father or
the husband does. And that's the act of voiding the vows.
But isn't it either way there's no back? Let's say in the
same day he says "I'm good with it" and then "No, no,
now I want to מפר meifer it." Can you do that, the
same day? No, right.
Or that's the whole point, or the other way around. Or מפר
meifer it and actually, you know what, I really wanted it to
keep- go- whatever which way you go?
Well, we'll talk about הקמה hakama after הפרה. hafara. Okay, so let's
take a look- but actually you're right, because we're going to get
a complicated- but as a general rule that is correct. You can't-
once you do one, it's over and done
with, except for תוך כדי דיבור, toch k'dei dibbur, it's over and
done with. So let's start and take a look at our new
פרק, perek, bottom of ס"ו ע"ב. samech-vav amud-beis. נערה המאורסה
אביה ובעלה מפירין נדריה. na'ara ha-me'orasa aviha u-ba'alah mefirin nedareha. So if
this is a woman that is actually in a middle space, not
independent of father and not yet have a husband, which is twelve
and a half, she's a בוגרת- bogeres no she actually has both
a father and a husband at the same time. She's twelve, is
that right? She
is a נערה, na'ara, yes, she's a נערה na'ara because so she's
twelve, but she's not yet twelve and a half so she's not
yet independent.
And she got- she's מאורסה, me'orasa, she is קידושין kiddushin but she
doesn't have נישואין. nisuin. If she has נישואין nisuin she started living
חופה chuppah together with her husband and the father's out of the
picture. But until she starts living together with her husband, you know
the classic חופה, chuppah, נישואין nisuin is the handing over, the going
from the father's house to the groom's house. So in a very
physical way and conceptual way, before נישואין nisuin she's still under the
father's control. Okay? And actually as the גמרא Gemara is going to
say or the ר"ן Ran says and others, actually פשט pshat of
this, פשט pshat of the תורה Torah is that before נישואין nisuin
the husband has no room. I mean yes, she's a married woman
and if she commits adultery she's חייב מיתה, chayav misa, etc., etc.
But in terms of whose control she's under, the פשט pshat is
only the father's. But nevertheless we are now creating a situation- I
say now we- we are saying that when she's in that state
of קידושין kiddushin and not נישואין, nisuin, that actually puts her also
to some small degree under the husband's control as well. Okay? If
she was a בוגרת, bogeres, then she would be completely out of
the father's control. If she was a קטנה, ktanah, it would also
work except by the קטנה ktanah you would have the question of
why would the נדר neder be binding? She's not yet an adult.
So let's take a look at one line in the ר"ן, Ran,
okay, where it says-
let's look at the first- the ר"ן Ran says the following. נערה
המאורסה אביה
ובעלה מפירין נדריה, na'ara ha-me'orasa aviha u-ba'alah mefirin nedareha, אפילו נדרים
שנדרה בעודה פנויה. afilu nedarim she-nadra b'odah penuyah. Okay, first of all,
the- the husband, the ארוס, arus, right, which is betrothed, the groom,
he actually can void even things that
were from before they had the
קידושין. kiddushin. מעיקרא קודם, mey-ikara koden, he and- he can void things
that existed prior even though they weren't- they came before the קידושין,
kiddushin, בשותפותא דאב b'shutfuta d'av together with the partnership of the father,
as the
גמרא Gemara says. דנערה דנקט לאפוקי בוגרת, d'na'ara d'nakat l'apukey bogeres, it
excludes the case of a בוגרת, bogeres, twelve and a half, דאין
אביה רשות בה, d'ein aviha rishus bah, there she's out of the
father's control. ואינו מפר נדריה, v'einu meifer nedareha, he wouldn't be part
of it. וארוס נמי בלא שותפותא דאב לא מצי מפר. ve-arus nami
b'lo shutfuta d'av lo matzi meifer.
Now listen to this, that's an important conceptual point. She's a בוגרת
bogeres and an ארוסה. arusa. Okay, so you would think father's out
of the picture, she's an ארוסה, arusa, the ארוס arus should now
void it. But the answer is no, because why not? Like just
get the father out, now it's all the husband? Because bottom line
is the husband being in the husband's house and the husband having
control is really only at the time of נישואין. nisuin. אירוסין erusin
is the- the guy, the husband does not really have any control,
she's not conceptually in his house. So by אירוסין erusin the- so
that when there's not yet נישואין nisuin the idea is this fundamentally
it's the father that voids it. Okay, it's a big
חידוש chiddush that... Okay, but if there’s no father around, then the
ארוס Arus doesn’t have any any any role. Okay, so that’s a
very important conceptual point. Since she’s still a נערה Naara and she’s
not נשואה, Nesuah, she’s fundamentally in the father’s house, fundamentally it’s the
father that voids it, but the ארוס, Arus, he needs the ארוס
Arus to go along. Okay, he needs, but fundamentally it’s the father.
By the way, the other point that’s relevant to this, it just
slipped out of my head is—oh yes, that’s why the ארוס’s Arus
נדרים Nedarim are קודמין, Kodmin, because normally in a case of a
woman who’s נשואה, Nesuah, if she says, oh by the way, a
minute before our wedding, a minute before the חופה Chupah I took
a נדר, Neder, okay, he cannot, the husband, when it's a real
full marriage, cannot void it. He can only void things that were
done during their marriage. So why can the ארוס Arus void things
from before the אירוסין? Erusin? So what’s the answer? Because it’s really
the husband who’s, it’s really the father who’s doing this. Okay, so
that’s important. Since it’s really the father, who cares if it was
before this marriage to the ארוס? Arus? You’re not the primary person.
So you need the father to be around. If the father isn’t
around, right, then if she’s a בוגרת Bogeret or the father died
or whatever, the ארוס Arus can do nothing. But because it’s fundamentally
the father, it can be even things from before. Okay, so very,
here we’re like laying the conceptual foundations.
Could be קודמין Kodmin also?
Well, no, but it could be the same day, but there’s no
קודמין. Kodmin. There’s no time before. It has to be יום שמעו,
Yom Shamo, that’s a different story, but not קודמין Kodmin means קודמין
Kodmin to the relationship, okay? Doesn’t mean the amount of time. Just
קודמין Kodmin to the relationship.
So what we're saying is really it's the father who the husband
tags on to
the participation of the ארוס. Arus.
Exactly. And that's what we're going to see when we look at
the פסוקים. Psukim. The פסוקים Psukim don't, you're not going to have
any idea where they got this out of the פסוקים. Psukim. Okay,
the פסוקים Psukim make it very clear there's basically only the father.
But somehow we're reading in, after אירוסין, Erusin, you need him to
do it as well.
Oh, so they're going to see it as דאורייתא. Deoraisa.
Right, they're going to see it as דאורייתא, Deoraisa, but certainly not
פשט Pshat of the פסוק. Pasuk. Okay, so we'll look at that
in a minute. And now one last line.
ומה דתנן Umah Ditnan אבל הוא הדין נמי דבת אחת עשרה שנה
Aval Hu HaDin Nami DeBas Achas Esre Shana שנדריה נבדקים SheNedareha Nivdakim
דאב וארוס מפירין נדריה. DeAv VeArus Mefirin Nedareha. It's not limited to
a נערה, Naara, it would also include a קטנה, Ketana, but not
any קטנה, Ketana, an 11-year-old. Why? Because one other הלכה Halacha by
נדרים Nedarim which we haven't mentioned, and we're already sixty almost seventy
דפים Dapim in, is that if somebody a year before בר או
בת מצוה Bar Or Bas Mitzvah makes a נדר, Neder, it would
be binding. Okay, and this is understood to be דאורייתא. Deoraisa. Okay,
we'll see about this. So if a girl makes it while she's
in
her 12th year, after 11 years and one day, it is binding,
and then that would be a case by a קטנה Ketana which
would have a נדר, Neder, and in that case it would be
the same הלכה, Halacha, that the father and the ארוס. Arus. Okay,
but what you see here is that fundamentally it is the father.
Even if you have a very smart קטן Katan who's 10 and
will make a נדר. Neder. Correct. Okay, you have to, there still
is a formal age point. So back to the
משנה. Mishnah. נערה המאורסה אביה ובעלה מפירין נדריה. Na'ara ham'urasa aviha u'va'ala
mafirin nedareha. The father together with the groom is
מיפר Mefer the נדר. Neder. הפר האב ולא הפר הבעל, הפר הבעל
ולא הפר האב, אינו מופר. Heifer HaAv Velo Heifer HaBaal, Heifer HaBaal
Velo Heifer HaAv, Eino Mufar. Okay, if one does it without the
other, it doesn't work. ואין צריך לומר שקיים אחד מהם. VeEin Tzarich
Lomar SheKiyam Echad Mehem. If one of them is מקיים Mekayem it,
actively says I'm good with it, I establish it, then of course
that makes it impossible to do, because if you need it as
הפרה, Hafarah, then if he does הקמה, Hakamah, you're stuck. Okay, so
let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. First it's going to
parse the משנה, Mishnah, then it's going to get back to the
פסוקים. Psukim. Says the גמרא, Gemara, היי רישא, Hai Reisha, אביה ובעלה
מפירין נדריה. Aviha UVaalah Mefirin Nedareha. So why do you have to
say הפר האב ולא הפר הבעל, הפר הבעל ולא הפר האב? Heifer
HaAv Velo Heifer HaBaal, Heifer HaBaal Velo Heifer HaAv? So it says
the obvious answer, מהו דתימא או אביה או בעלה, Mahhu Detima O
Aviha O Baalah, one might have said or meant either one could
do it. קא משמע לן Ka Mashma Lan that it's not either,
you need both of them to do it. Clear enough. ואין צריך
לומר שקיים אחד מהם, VeEin Tzarich Lomar SheKiyam Echad Mehem, and it
goes without
saying if one of them is מקיים Mekayem it. Goes without saying?
Exactly. למה לי למתנא? Lamah Li LeMatna? Why do you have to
teach that? השתא יש לומר הפר זה בלא זה בלא כלום, Hashta
Yesh Lomar Heifer Zeh Belo Zeh Belo Klum, if one does it
and the other does nothing, it doesn't work. קיים אחד מהם למה
לי? Kiyam Echad Mehem Lamah Li? Of course you know if one
of them is מקיים, Mekayem, of course you know that's why it
says ואין צריך לומר, VeEin Tzarich Lomar, but
you know, it's such a
funny גמרא. Gemara. Okay, ואין צריך לומר, VeEin Tzarich Lomar, so why
are you saying it?
All right, so the גמרא Gemara says, צריכא. Tzaricha. למה לי למיתני?
lama li lemisnei? Why do I have to teach it? דאצטריכא ליה,
de'itztreicha lei, כגון דהיכא דאחד מהם מקיים ואחד מהם, kegon deheicha de'echad
mehem mekayem ve'echad mehem, one, let’s call them A and B because
it doesn’t matter here which is the אב av and which is
the בעל. baal. Okay, A and B. Anyway, one of them, כגון
דהיכא דאחד מהם מיפר אחד. kegon deheicha de'echad mehem meifer echad. So
A went ahead and was מיפר, meifer, and B, I’m going to
follow B, and B was מקיים. mekayem. Now,
alright, but so fine and destroy so. וחזר המקיים ונשאל על הקמתו.
vechazar hamekayem venishal al hakamaso. So here’s a crazy idea. I mean
it’s more crazy than that you could do התרת נדרים, hataras nedarim,
but you could also do a התרה על הקמה.
hatara al
hakamah. Okay, הקמה hakamah is a verbal act that has this impact
that it’s going to affirm the נדר. neder. So you can basically
say you know if I really had thought it through I wouldn’t
have been מקיים mekayem it, I was just doing it by this
and that. Okay fine, we’ll be מתיר matir the הקמה. hakamah. You
weren’t thinking, it was a הקמה בטעות, hakamah b’taus, but it uses
the same mechanism and we can retroactively be מתיר matir the הקמה.
hakamah.
So then he’s doing it at a later date than when he
first heard?
It doesn’t need to. Oh, it’ll be the same day?
Yeah. Oh, okay, so he still has to do it the same
day.
Yeah. Let’s for now not worry about timing but for argument’s sake
we’ll say everything is on the same day. Okay. We’ll worry about
timing later. Okay, so he went ahead and he did הקמה. hakamah.
Okay, A was מיפר, meifer, B did הקמה, hakamah, then B got
rid of the הקמה. hakamah. Okay, so now let B do a
הפרה hafara and a story. Okay. וחזר המקיים ונשאל על הקמתו. vechazar
hamekayem venishal al hakamaso. מהו דתימא מאי דמיפר מעיקרא השתא ואימא. ma’u
d’seima mai d’meifer me’ikara hashta ve’eima. So we’d think, look what he
was מיפר, meifer, what he did he now reversed, so we’re back
to square one, do a הפרה hafara and everybody would be happy.
He uprooted what he did. קמשמע לן דבעינן שניהם בבת אחת. kmashmalan
deba’inan shneichem b’vas achas. No, we start again from square one, they
both have to do a הפרה. hafara. Why? The logic is the
following. I mean it’s a very terse גמרא. Gemara. But the logic
is, I’m sorry, the ר"ן, Ran, let me say, let me say,
so let me just clarify then I’ll tell you the logic. What
it’s saying is once he does a הקמה hakamah then you cannot
have the, B did a הקמה, hakamah, then it got reversed, and
then B did a הפרה. hafara. That הפרה hafara that B did
after this reversal of the הקמה hakamah cannot combine with the הפרה
hafara that came before the הקמה. hakamah. Since they have to come
together, right? A and B’s הפרה hafara have to sort of join
together. The fact that there was an act of הקמה hakamah in
between, even though its impact was undone, but that act of the
הקמה hakamah says you cannot that that הפרה hafara sort of there
was a period where that הפרה hafara became like meaningless. Okay A
did הפרה, hafara, B did הקמה. hakamah. In real world terms, even
retroactively this will be true. But in real world terms as we
were experiencing that, right? A’s הפרה hafara now had dissipated, had lost
any power, it had no potential to be הלכתית halachically effective now,
right? You understand that? Right? Because B did הקמה. hakamah. So now
okay, and the story, what A did now means nothing. So now
retroactively even though we’ve avoided that act, you can’t go ahead and
give that its power
you
know its power now to combine. So A would have to go
back and do another הפרה. hafara. But
wait, why is the reason for saying this in any case?
And so then
now wait one minute, one minute, why like the you know like
where do we get that from? You know what’s motivating the גמרא?
Gemara? You could say that, you could say the other thing, like
nobody knows. The גמרא Gemara is just like asserting it. Not only
does nobody know, I mean it’s not spelling out its logic, but
the רמב"ם Rambam even takes this further. רמב"ם Rambam says not only
now is it true that A’s act before the הקמה hakamah isn’t
good, but A cannot now do another הפרה. hafara. The same way
you can’t do a הפרה hafara after הקמה hakamah or הקמה hakamah
after הפרה hafara which was a מחלוקת, machlokes, once you did one
obviously it’s too late to do the other. You can’t do a
הפרה hafara after הפרה. hafara. You only get one chance. So since
your initial הפרה hafara you sort of lost its power, didn’t work,
tough luck you’re out. Why? I don’t know, it sounds strange
that you would do הקמה hakamah and then שאלה sha’ala on the
הקמה. hakamah. Right.
Like the one who, do a שאלה sha’ala on the first הפרה,
hafara, so then it’s not like so you get another guy
doing הקמה hakamah on the first guy’s.
Right. Right. I don’t know, I don’t know, it’s very abstract and
theoretically. Yes, exactly. So anyway but that’s the רמב"ם. Rambam. Let’s not
even go to the רמב"ם. Rambam. But before the רמב"ם, Rambam, let’s
just talk about one other point which the ר"ן Ran asks, which
is, I don’t get it says the ר"ן. Ran. This whole thing
works retroactively.
So if it works retroactively then looking back and knowing it just
I mean. But wait no, the התרה hatara of the הקמה hakamah
works retroactively, I’m sorry. So it’s like George Orwell’s 1984, right? We’ve
changed history so now we’re going to rewrite what happened there. So
rewriting it, there was no הקמה. hakamah. So why is there something
that’s an obstacle now of combining those two? Combining the two הפרות
*hafarot* and he even gives examples of basically if I go ahead
and I'm מקדש *mekadesh* a woman and I say הרי את מקודשת
לי על מנת שאין עליך נדרים nedarim. *harei at mekudeshet li al
menat she-ein alayich nedarim* עלי אלו נדרים nedarim. *alai eilu nedarim* and
she has נדרים nedarim *nedarim* and she accepts the ring and then
she goes later that day and she goes to a חכם *chacham*
and she gets a התרה *hatara* on her נדר neder *neder*. So
retroactively you know or a week or whatever a week later she
goes and gets a התרה *hatara*. Retroactively a week ago when I
gave her the ring now retroactively she doesn't have נדרים nedarim *nedarim*.
So the קידושין Kiddushin, *kiddushin* is good. Okay that's the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* because that's what it means retroactively we look back at it
and we realize now that we've undone it in hindsight we see
that there was never נדרים nedarim *nedarim*. So he says so why
is this different? Okay? So so he says
my answer to that question was even though the הקמה hakama. *hakama*
didn't have an effect the very act of doing the הקמה hakama.
*hakama* might just be enough to create an obstacle. You didn't change
the fact that I did the act. Like when we say I
was מתיר *matir* my נדר neder *neder* retroactively you didn't change the
fact that the word came out of my mouth. It just says
that they were never binding. Okay so maybe the act of the
הקמה hakama, *hakama* is enough to create an obstacle. That's sort of
what I suggest. The ר"ן Ran *Ran* also says that the problem
is is that it's such a weak thing the הפרה hafara *hafara*.
The הפרה hafara, *hafara* that A did number one it's not a
physical act like קידושין Kiddushin. *kiddushin* it's just words it's very abstract
it has nothing concrete and it's not even binding yet. It's waiting
for this other הפרה hafara, *hafara* to combine with it so that
it has some power. So that type of thing is so weak
he doesn't really explain the mechanism that even if retroactively we undo
the הקמה hakama, *hakama* somehow that's you know lost its potential power.
The fact that it passed through a period in real time even
though not retroactive time where it wasn't able to be effective it
like loses its power. Anyway whether you understand that answer I don't
fully understand it but I want you to appreciate that this line
this חידוש chidush *chiddush* that the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* has here in
a very terse not clear way it's like it's not clear what's
you know the mechanism what's the logic and so on. But nevertheless
that's the הלכה halachic *halacha*. The הלכה *halacha* is that you do
a הקמה hakama *hakama* even if retroactively you undo it the very
fact that that act of הקמה hakama, *hakama* was done is an
obstacle for the two הפרות *hafarot* to combine. And therefore A would
have to do another הפרה hafara *hafara* if you want the הפרה
hafara.
*hafara* to be... and so the חידוש chidush *chiddush* of the משנה
Mishnah: *mishna* was so we don't need to tell you when it
was מקיים mekayeim *mekayeim*
even if the case where he... no the ר"ן Ran *Ran* asks
what do you mean you don't need to tell me you do
need to tell me this הלכה *halacha* who would have thought of
this הלכה *halacha*? So that's it we don't need to tell you
a simple case of הקמה *hakama* because obviously it won't work. Okay?
But why are we mentioning הקמה *hakama* so that you'll realize that
sometimes הקמה *hakama* can create an obstacle. What can I tell you?
Alright anyway that's the idea. So what we've learned here is the
idea that number one you can do a התרה *hatara* on a
הקמה *hakama* and what we've and what we've also learned is again
you know the bottom line that if he did this הקמה *hakama*
even if retroactively it was undone it serves as the obstacle for
the two הפרות *hafarot* to combine.
But it may or may not be able to be an obstacle
that you can get around depending if you're the רמב"ם *Rambam*.
Exactly. Now we're going to spend the rest of the day trying
to figure out where חז"ל Chazal *Chazal* get it in the פסוקים
psukim *pesukim*. So let's actually look at the פסוקים psukim, *pesukim*. Okay
everybody go there some חומש *Chumash* there or if you have the
ArtScroll they have the whole thing in the ArtScroll. Okay so let's
just read the פסוקים pesukim. *pesukim* here the beginning of מטות *Matot*
together. וידבר משה
אל ראשי המטות לבני ישראל לאמר זה הדבר אשר צוה
ה' *vayedaber moshe el rashei hamatot livnei yisrael lemor zeh hadavar asher
tziva Hashem*. Now by the way I should say that the idea
of ראשי המטות *rashei hamatot* is important because it becomes a little
bit of a peg why why דווקא *davka* ראשי המטות *rashei hamatot*
normally you say בני ישראל *bnei yisrael* so it becomes a little
bit of a peg for חז"ל Chazal *Chazal* to say oh the
idea of some people in positions of authority have a role here
is a little hint to the idea of התרה *hatara*. Even though
this is all this is all הפרה *hafara* the תורה Torah *Torah*
never speaks about התרה *hatara* we've never even discussed in the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* where we get the idea of התרה *hatara*.
I don't think the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* discussed it. I'm going to
have to see. Anyway so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this...
maybe it did and I'm forgetting. Okay what? The גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says like this. Did I say that? Oh that's pretty hilarious that's
pretty good Freudian. So the so the תורה Torah *Torah* says like
this. איש כי ידר נדר neder. לה' או השבע שבעה לאסר אסר
על נפשו לא יחל דברו ככל היצא מפיו יעשה *ish ki yidor
neder la-Hashem o hishava shevua le-esor issar al nafsho lo yachel devaro
ke-chol ha-yotze mipiv ya'aseh*. This is what we've been dealing with. You
make a נדר neder *neder* or שבועה shavua *shevua* a man thank
you so therefore and it's interesting that the assumption is the effect
of it is making something forbidden so here you have both a
נדר neder. *neder* and שבועה shavua. *shevua* obviously in another context but
here specifically it's made them forbidden which is obviously the assumption throughout
our מסכת *masechet*. That it can you know he cannot nullify his
words he must do like he says a מצות עשה *mitzvot aseh*
and מצות לא תעשה *mitzvot lo ta'aseh*. And this is the בל
יחל *bal yachel* right of any violation of a נדר neder, *neder*.
That's a man and that's the story right you have the whole
פסוק pasuk, *pasuk*. Right. והאשה *ve-ha-isha* but a woman who is under
control of one man or another כי תדר נדר neder. לה' ואסרה
אסר בבית bveit, אביה בנעריה *ki tidor neder la-Hashem ve-asra issar be-veit
aviha bi-neureiha* okay so there you have the idea of a נערה
*na'ara* and בית beis אביה *veit aviha*. ושמע אביה את נדרה ואסרה
אשר *ve-shama aviha et nidra ve-asra asher* והחריש לה אביה. V'hecherish lah
aviha. The father hears the נדר and notice, by the way, the
שבועה shavua, aspect drops off even though it started with a שבועה.
shavua, Right, so that works very much to reinforce what we've been
learning about, that a נדר is focusing on objects and makes an
object forbidden. Like שבועה, shavua. you could make something forbidden but that's
not the fundamental like scope of a שבועה, the fundamental use of
a שבועה. So interesting that the Torah itself would switch to נדר.
Okay, so he hears the נדר and the prohibition that she made
prohibited, והחריש לה V'hecherish lah. אביה. וקמו כל נדריה וכל איסר אשר
אסרה על נפשה יקום. V'kamu kol nedareha v'chol issar asher asra al
nafsha yakum. Then they are established, the two-lay. And that's okay. ואם
הניא אביה אותה ביום שמעו. V'im hini aviha osa b'yom sham'o. But
if he annulled it, another word הניא hini is annulled it, ביום
שמעו, b'yom sham'o, the day he hears it, so clearly we've got
one day. כל נדריה ואסריה אשר אסרה על נפשה לא יקום. Kol
nedareha v'essareha asher asra al nafsha lo yakum. Then they will not
be established. וה' יסלח לה. V'Hashem yislach lah. God will forgive her,
כי הניא אביה אותה, ki hini aviha osa, because her father annulled
it. A lot of times, why does she need to be forgiven?
She didn't necessarily transgress it. Had she transgressed it before the father
annulled it? Or no, no, no, they don't say that. Then why
does God forgive her if she didn't really violate? No, they say
different. They say the father annulled it, but she wasn't aware that
the father annulled it and she went ahead and she violated it.
Okay, so on the one hand she didn't do an עבירה, aveira,
but on the other hand her intention in her mind psychologically she
did do an עבירה. aveira. So
she still needs God to forgive
because, even if there was no מעשה עבירה, ma'aseh aveira, the גברא
gavra she perceived it as an עבירה aveira anyway. So that's how
חז"ל Chazal read it. Okay, so there you have the days, the
years, the father annuls it. You don't have the father doing an
active הקמה. You do have him either passively not annulling it or
annulling it. Okay, then it continues: ואם היה תהיה לאיש. V'im hayo
sihyeh l'ish. If she becomes to a man.
Now
the simple sense of תהיה, sihyeh, although for people
who learn
קידושין, Kiddushin, מקיש הויה לכתיבה או הויה ליציאה, makish havayah l'chativah o
havayah l'yetziah, ויצאה והיתה. v'yatz'ah v'hay'sa. The גמרא Gemara thinks that תהיה
sihyeh often means קידושין. kiddushin, But פשט pshat of the Torah is
תהיה sihyeh means נישואין. Nissu'in. Okay? So if she becomes to a
man, so that's actually נישואין. Nissu'in. She gets married, not just קידושין,
kiddushin not just betrothed. ונדריה
עליה. V'nedareha aleha. Her vows from beforehand from her father's house are
on her. או מבטא שפתיה אשר אסרה על נפשה. O mivta sefaseha
asher asra al nafsha. What the ו vov is? It seems like
just a repetition. Or the uttering of her lips. Okay, ושמע אישה
ביום שמעו. V'shama isha b'yom sham'o.
And her husband hears again on the day that he hears. והחריש
לה. And he's silent. וקמו נדריה ואסריה אשר אסרה על נפשה יקמו.
V'kamu nedareha v'essareha asher asra al nafsha yakumu. Then it's established. ואם
ביום שמע אישה יניא אותה. V'im b'yom sh'mo isha yani osa. But
if he annulled it, והפר את נדרה אשר עליה ואת מבטא שפתיה
אשר אסרה על נפשה. V'heifer es nidrah asher aleha v'es mivta sefaseha
asher asra al nafsha. And he annuls them. וה' יסלח לה. V'Hashem
yislach lah. Then fine, it'll be annulled. Okay,
so basically the husband can annul even if she has the vows
from her father's house, right? So it says נדריה עליה. nedareha aleha.
Now let's say she has no man in control of her. What
would be that case? Would that be the case that David mentioned
that she was orphaned and not married? But the more standard case
is ונדר אלמנה וגרושה. V'neder almanah u'grushah. Okay, so she went from
her father's house to her husband's house and now the husband is
not in the picture. He died or divorced. Then כל אשר אסרה
על נפשה יקום עליה. kol asher asra al nafsha yakum aleha. Then
you can't get out of it, you're bound, right?
Nobody can annul. Now, so it seems like we should be done.
No, because we didn't do the case of what happens if she
does a new נדר.
Okay, so that's fine. So if it's a new
נדר, ואם בית אישה נדרה. V'im beis isha nadra. If she takes
a vow when she's in her husband's house. בית clearly means after
נישואין. Nissu'in. And that's the first taking of the vow. או אסרה
איסר על נפשה בשבועה. O asra issar al nafsha b'shavua. ושמע אישה
והחריש לה. V'shama isha v'hecherish lah. And the husband hears and is
silent, ולא הניא אותה, v'lo hinya osa, וקמו כל נדריה וכל איסר
אשר אסרה על נפשה יקום. v'kamu kol nedareha v'chol issar asher asra
al nafsha yakum. Then it'll be established. ואם הפר יפר אותם אישה
ביום שמעו. V'im haifer yaifer osam isha b'yom sham'o.
But
if he annuls it, on the day he hears, כל מוצא שפתיה
לנדריה ולאיסר נפשה לא יקום. kol motza sefaseha l'nedareha v'l'issar nafsha lo
yakum. Then it's not established. אישה הפרם, Isha haiferam, the husband annulled
it, וה' יסלח לה. V'Hashem yislach lah. Now Michael said I don't
get it. It's redundant. If a husband can annul it, why do
you have to say it twice? And not only that, but a
better question: if he can annul something from before when it was
out of his control, certainly he can annul something that was done
under his control. So it's because of this redundancy
that חז"ל Chazal read the first פרשה, parsha, the first paragraph, to
be about an ארוסה. arusa. Okay? So because if the first paragraph
was about a נישואין Nissu'in and the husband could annul things that
preceded, then you wouldn't have needed the last paragraph.
And it sends a משנה: the father and the husband.
I have a problem with it. A couple of problems. First of
all, it says היה תהיה לאיש. hayo sihyeh l'ish. It sounds like
it's נישואין. Nissu'in. It only mentions the husband. It doesn't mention the
father. So there's a lot of manipulation that we've got to do
in order to make it that case. But because it appears to
be redundant, if you look at the רמב"ן Ramban on this
פרשה, parsha, he says the פשט pshat of this is that it's
the husband. Not the father, it's נישואין, nissu'in, and it but then
it would make the other things sort of redundant. But nevertheless, repetitive,
but nonetheless that's the פשט, p'shat, he says, but because otherwise it
would make it repetitive, חז"ל Chazal, have read this to be about
an ארוסה, arusa, and read it about that the father's also involved,
as we actually said the father's primary. Okay, and then he ends
his discussion by
saying: והקבלה תכריע. V'hakabalah tachria. Which is like our tradition has the
final word. Like, you can tell he's not totally happy, it's not
the פשט, p'shat, but okay. Either way he has a
problem, but in some ways you would say I'd rather be a
little repetitive than to say something completely different from what it means.
But that's what חז"ל Chazal say. Okay, so they say that it's
going to be talking about an ארוסה, arusa, and how do they
get the father in? The ר"ן Ran says it's all about the
vav. Because it says, when it says ואם היו תהיה לאיש, v'im
hayo tihye l'ish, which means for those who are allowed, means that
and the vav connects it to the father. So if she's מאורסת
איש, m'urasat ish, it's connected to the previous thing, the father's still
the bearer in the פרשה, parsha, but also now the husband in
the פרשה. parsha. So that's what we wind up doing. So let's
take a look now at the גמרא. Gemara Okay. So גמרא Gemara
says like this: נערה המאורסה Naara HaMeorasah אביה ובעלה מפירין נדריה. Aviha
UVaalah Mefirin Nedareha. מנלן? Minalan? Where do you know this from? אמר
רבה, Amar Rabbah, or Rava says it, דאמר קרא: d'amar kra: ואם
היו תהיה לאיש ונדריה עליה. V'im hayo tihye l'ish u'nedareha aleha. מכאן
לנערה המאורסה
שאביה ובעלה מפירין נדריה.
Mikan l'na'ara
ham'urasa she'aviha u'va'ala mafirin nedareha. So here it is, it's right in
the פסוק, pasuk I don't understand where. Okay, so the ר"ן Ran
says essentially what we just said. He said: clearly it can't be
about a נישואין, nissua, because then it would be completely, then the
תורה Torah would be completely repetitive. So therefore it's got to be
about a נערה מאורסה. na'ara m'urasa. Now, how do you know even
if you said it's an ארוסה, arusa, what's pushing you to say
that it's the father, since the תורה Torah talks about the husband?
So the ר"ן Ran says like we were saying earlier:
Because fundamentally the father is the one in control, right? When she's
before נישואין, nissu'in, after אירוסין erusin it doesn't matter, the father is
really, she's really in no other way conceptually in her under her
husband's under her groom's, let's call him groom, under her groom's control.
Okay. So therefore even if we're going to read this to be
talking about a נערה מאורסה na'ara m'urasa and the תורה's Torah talking
about the husband slash groom's power, we are going to refuse to
take the father off the table. We know as a principle that
before נישואין, nissu'in, she's in her father's house, she's in her father's
control. So therefore we're going to this פרשה parsha we're going to
say is about נערה מאורסה na'ara m'urasa and we're going to say
it's both the father and the husband and the groom. Okay. So
now the גמרא Gemara goes like this: אימא האי קרא בנישואין כתיב?
Eima hai kra bi'nesua k'tia? Now the גמרא's Gemara going to work
it through. I don't get it, just say the פסוק's Pasuk talking
about a נישואין. nesua. אי משום נישואין? I mishum nesua? No, if
it was a נישואין, nesua, קרא אחרינא כתיב, kra achina ktiv, then
it's repetitive. And because we have it later, at the end of
the פרשה, parsha, ובית אישה נדרה. v'veit isha nadara. And it's in
her husband's house, right? And if you've already said that he's מפר
הכל, mefer hakol, then certainly, then
the second thing is completely repetitive, unnecessary. So the גמרא Gemara says:
אימא תרווייהו בנישואין. Eima tavayhu bi'nesua. Okay, let's let both of them
be about a נישואין. nesua. וכי תימא תרי קראי בנישואין למה לי?
V'chi teima trei krai bi'nesua lama li? Why would I need two
פסוקים pesukim about נישואין? nesua? Two paragraphs? למימר L'meimar to tell me
שאין הבעל מפר בקודמין. she'eina ba'al mefer b'kodmin. Because when it says
ובית אישה נדרה, v'veit isha nadara, right, that's telling you that it
has to be in her husband's house, it can't be from before.
So maybe they're both talking about a נישואין, nesua, and it's telling
me that it's only about new נדרים. nedarim Of course the problem
is how can
it
be telling me, it says ונדריה עליה, u'nedareha aleha, right? It's very
bizarre. Okay. And the גמרא Gemara doesn't fully sort of work that
out, but anyway it says that doesn't answer the question about being
repetitive. Even if somehow we manage to bracket ונדריה עליה, u'nedareha aleha,
and I don't know how we would do that, it wouldn't explain
why I need both
פרשיות. parshiyos. סוף סוף למה לי. Sof sof lama li. So you
have anyway, okay, so let the second one be talking about נישואין,
nesua, telling you the חידוש chiddush that שאין הבעל מפר בקודמין, eina
ba'al mefer b'kodmin, only new ones. So now go back, why do
you need the first פרשה? parsha? Right? You'd be seeing the same
thing again. Okay. Same you don't need both פרשיות. parshiyos. And don't
tell me the second one teaches you something new, because if the
second one teaches you something new, then okay then I didn't need
the first one. Okay. So I don't need both of them. Now
again the גמרא's Gemara point that it's redundant.
Okay, it doesn't point out the point that we also said that
the רמב"ן Ramban says, which is it's
actually a bit of a bigger חידוש chiddush because the first one
seems like it's even earlier נדרים. All right. So now the גמרא
Gemara continues. אי בעית
אימא, I ba'it eima, or if you want, I'll tell you the
following: הווייה כקידושין משמע. Hava'ah k'iddushin mashma. Since it says ואם היו
תהיה לאיש, v'im hayo tihye l'ish, הווייה תהיה hava'ah tihyeh means קידושין,
kiddushin. means betrothal, not נישואין. nissu'in. So therefore that's pushing us to
read it as אירוסין. erusin. Now by the way, the ר"ן Ran
says: what do you mean? Even according to the גמרא's Gemara פשט
pshat of the פסוקים, pesukim. הווייה hava'ah often means נישואין. nissu'in. Okay.
It can mean both, but because it can also mean אירוסין erusin
according to חז"ל, Chazal so we're going to read it in this
more expansive way that's including the
cases of. And since the second פרשה Parshah tells us that the
husband does not do earlier vows, and the first one, that's how
we read the second one in light of the first one. And
the first one tells us about נדרה עליה nedareiha aleiha he can
do earlier vows. We're going to read the first one about אירוסין
Erusin and the second one about נישואין, Nisuin, right? That's, so that's
a difference, right? The first one explicitly says that he can do
earlier vows, נדרה עליה. nedareiha aleiha. The second one is an explicit,
but חז"ל chazal, read the second one to say he can't do
earlier vows, only בית אישה, beisa ishah, only בית אישה beisa ishah
is when he has the power. So how do you reconcile that?
Okay, so the first one is about אירוסין Erusin and the reason
it can be earlier is because fundamentally it's the father. And the
second one is about נישואין. Nisuin. All right, so that's how, and
therefore it can only be new vows. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like
this, אימא דהוי אב לחודיה מיפר.
Eima dehavai av lechudei
meifer. Okay, so now that we're reading it about a נערה מאורסה,
na'arah me'orasah, this first paragraph in the beginning, let's say only the
father. Now again, how do you say only the father? Because the
פסוק says the husband. אם כן, Im kein, ואסרה איסר בבית אביה
יניא
אותה,
ve'asra issar bveit aviha
yani osa, no, ואסרה איסר בבית, ve'asra issar bveit, how do you
read this? Hold
on, בבית אביה בנעוריה. bveit aviha b'neuraha. Wait,
I'm just trying to read the words
properly. ואסרה איסר בבית, ve'asra issar bveit, so it's got the בבית,
בבית אביה בנעוריה. bveit aviha b'neuraha. Okay, so the ר"ן
is saying the גמרא Gemara is reading it like this. It's completely
bizarre. So we're reading it, but the ר"ן says this is coming
from the fact that the groom should really have no power. We've
chosen to read this to be about an ארוסה, arusah, but we
also know that as a הלכה principle the groom has no power.
So even if we're reading it about an ארוסה, arusah, why don't
we read it the following way? Why don't we read it that
you don't need the groom to annul? Really it's the father annulling,
and the reason the תורה Torah mentions the groom is to tell
you that he can do a הקמה. If the groom does a
הקמה, he can, you know, like clog up the works now that
he's in the picture. But you don't need it. Okay, but if
he chooses to do a הקמה, then he'll clog up the works.
But let's still keep it fundamentally in the father's control if we're
going to read it about an ארוסה. arusah. So that's what the
גמרא Gemara says. Well, let's read that again. אימא אב לחודיה מיפר.
Eima av lechudei meifer. Let's,
if we're going to read it about that case, since she's only
an ארוסה, arusah, let's say that really it's totally the father and
the groom, even though the תורה Torah is talking about the groom
or whatever, that's really only very secondary. He's not really necessary. אם
כן, Im kein, no, that's true, ואסרה איסר בבית אביה בנעוריה למה
לי. ve'asra issar bveit aviha b'neuraha lamah li. Why would I need
to tell me that in the first פרשה parshah that it would
be the father? If you're telling me that even after אירוסין Erusin
it's all the father, why would you need the פרשה parshah to
tell me that before אירוסין Erusin it's the father? השתא יש לומר
במקום ארוס מיפר אב לחודיה, Hashta yesh lomar bimkom arus meifer av
lechudei, if the father is really the only one doing it even
after אירוסין, Erusin, שלא במקום ארוס מבעיא? shelo bimkom arus mibaia? Would
you need to tell me שלא במקום ארוס? shelo bimkom arus? Of
course, it's such a bizarre question, first you need to establish the
first principle before you move on to the חידוש of the next
case of ארוס. arus. But what this shows you is that the
תורה says, the גמרא is saying like, okay fine, the פרשיות Parshiyos
are redundant, we have to say this one is talking about an
ארוסה, arusah, but we don't want to give up on our sort
of core idea that the groom has no control. So let's force
it to be all about the father. No, no, no, that's too
much violence to the verses. So we're going to allow here for
the fact that the groom also has a control. It's not just
the father. In the case of נערה מאורסה, na'arah me'orasah, and it
both draws on the earlier פרשה parshah and our general principles that
the father is in control, but it also says that the groom
also is in control and that you need both of them. So
now the גמרא does a complete reversal and the גמרא says like
this, אימא ארוס במקום ארוס לחודיה מיפר, Eima arus bimkom arus lechudei
meifer, which is actually much closer to the פשט pshat of the
פסוקים. psukim, Okay, so if we were suggesting to read it that
it's really all the father and starting a range of problems, let's
now try the reverse. Now let's say that the פשט pshat of
the פסוקים psukim is that it's really about the husband. So we're
really getting ready to read it to be about the groom. Let's
now read the פסוקים. psukim Fine, it's a נערה מאורסה, na'arah me'orasah,
and it's really all the groom now that does it. Maybe the
father's still a little bit in the picture that if he does
a הקמה he can ruin things. But why are we assuming that
they're both equal? Let's now follow פשט הפסוקים. pshat hapesukim. If we're
going to talk about an ארוס, arus, let it be that fundamentally
it's the groom and not the father. Okay? At least that would
be closer to the פשט הפסוקים. pshat hapesukim. Okay. So therefore, אליבא
דארוס, aliba d'arous, if it were the father, it would still need
the groom.
ארוס לאו בעל מיפר, arous lav baal meifer, but the groom doesn't
need the father, okay? So if you're going to read it about
a נערה המאורסה, naara hameourasa, then the Torah is explicitly saying that
it's the groom who does it. So fine, let's say it's really
all about the groom. הכי תימא דאכתביה רחמנא למה לי? hachi teima
de’achtaviah rachmana lama li? Okay,
then why is it sort of put in the father put in
the picture, the father in the פשט הפסוקים pshat hapesukim in the
picture? And חז"ל are somehow reading that the two פרשיות parshiyot are
tightly linked and נערה עליה, naara aleiha, so still seeing the father
somehow in addition
to the father's power being there anyway, also this ארוס arous has
a...
now of course you could say פשט הפסוקים pshat hapesukim is that
even though, here's what פשט pshat could be, even though she's carrying
the נדרים from her father's house, the father's out of the picture
and it's all about the husband, that's פשט. pshat. But we're again,
we're not prepared to give up the father's control because we know
that in general she really is in the father's conceptually the father's
house. So we're reading it that he's still involved. So if you
want to follow פשט הפסוקים pshat hapesukim that it's the groom that's
told that that would be the real one who did it, what's
the point, you know, what role does the father have? Because we're
not prepared to say father has no role. So the גמרא says,
למה לי? lama li? מיבעי ליה דהקים הוא כהקים. mibaei lei dehakeim
hu kehakeim. What we said earlier. Fine, he's not... you don't need
it, but he can muck up the works. Okay, if he does
a הקמה, right, then it will prevent it. So now, that's not
a bad read of the פסוקים, psukim, okay? We're going to read
it about a נערה המאורסה, naara hameourasa, not about a נשואה, nesuah,
and it can involve earlier נדרים because the father is still involved,
but fundamentally it's the husband, fundamentally it's the groom, father is a
little bit involved, he can make things a problem, but fundamentally it's
the groom. So that's a reasonable read, so why don't we say
that? אם כן, ובית אישה נדרה, למה כתבה? im kein, uveit ishah
nadara, lama katva?
So why did the תורה have to tell me the case of
a נשואה? nesuah? If in the case of an ארוסה arousa the
groom is totally in control, so the case of a נשואה, nesuah,
how much more so? קל וחומר. kal vachomer. ומה במקום אב, ארוס
מיפר לחודיה, u'mah bemakom av, arous meifer lechudei,
when there's a father and fundamentally she's seen in the father to
be in the father's house, and nevertheless the groom is really the
one who annuls it, שלא במקום אב מיבעיא? shelo bemakom av mibaeia?
After נישואין nisuin it's all חדא זימנא. chada zimna. And you wouldn't
need the Torah to tell me the father can't be מיפר meifer
because the father is totally out of the picture. Okay, so then
it would be completely redundant. So one way or another way, the
פסוקים here are going to be redundant. And the only way they're
not redundant is if we create a new model where it's not
the father only because that we already know from before she's in
the ארוס's arous house, if it's not the groom only, if it's
not the husband only, that we know by ובית אישה, uveit ishah,
so it's a case where it's both of them combined. Even though
it's both of them combined, again, I'll repeat that it's still fundamentally
the father, we're going to still keep our fundamental way of looking
at things where it is where she's in the father's control, okay,
until the נישואין. nisuin. But you do need the active participation of
the groom, not only can he muck it up, you need his
active participation, but it's still fundamentally the father and that's why it
works לתרווייהו. letarvaihu. And now the גמרא just concludes by saying, ואימה
ובית אישה נדרה לומר שאינו מיפר בקודמין. v’eima uveit ishah nadara lomar
she'eino meifer bekodmin. Hold on, let
me see this, let me see the גרסא. girsa. Yeah, hold on
a minute. ואימה, v’eima, why don't we say, ובית אישה נדרה לומר
שאינו מיפר בקודמין? uveit ishah nadara lomar she'eino meifer bekodmin?
So why don't we say, nah, you know what? Maybe the first
פרשה parsha about the groom, it's fundamentally the groom. Then you'll tell
me so then why would the Torah need to tell me the
case of נשואה? nesuah? It would need to tell me right, because
if the groom can do it, how much more so can the
husband do it? No, maybe it's telling me that in fact that
if that in the case by the husband, right, that it's he
can't do earlier ones, he can only do new ones. That's why
it has to tell me the case of the husband. Is everybody
with me? Right? We wanted to say that maybe the first פרשה
parsha is the groom. Okay, but if the groom can do it,
it's really all the groom. Who needs the פרשה parsha about the
husband? Nah, you need the פרשה parsha of the husband to tell
me the husband can't do it about earlier vows. ואימה ובית אישה
נדרה לומר שאינו מיפר בקודמין? v’eima uveit ishah nadara lomar she'eino meifer
bekodmin? So the גמרא says,
okay, but if we're telling me the husband can't do about earlier
vows, ומינה ארוס מיפר בקודמין. u'minah arous meifer bekodmin. Then I would
learn out that the ארוס arous implicitly can do earlier vows. So
we get back to the fact that then that sort of makes,
you know, first פרשה parsha repetitive or some reason bits me up.
You know, anyway, but let's just read it that way. It then
it would say to me that the ארוס arous can do earlier,
which would be sort of a bigger, you know, again make it
superfluous. אלא לאו משום שותפותא דאב. ela lav mishum shutfuta d'av. The
only way to get this as a something that's not repetitive or
not contradictory is to create this new reality of a partnership where
it's not fundamentally, well it is still the father is still the
base, but it's not all the father. You need the father combined
with the ארוס. arous. Even though it's both of them combined, again,
I'll repeat that it's still fundamentally the father, and that's why it
works לתרווייהו. letarvaihu. And that allows שותפין shutafin as opposed to the
נשואה nesuah which is not the שותפין, shutafin, and why this is
a separate פרשה parsha that in. I fully understand that because fundamentally
it's
the father, therefore the groom has zero power, שותפין? shutafin? I didn't
understand that.
Yeah,
the father's fundamentally the one who makes it. So we don't look
at it as שותפין shutafin because from the father's perspective it's not
שותפין. shutafin. It's basically the father was making it here, he just
needs the groom to sign off. Okay? So the fundamental act of
הפרה seems to be the father's. The evidence being when there's no
father and only a groom there can be no הפרה, right? So
he fundamentally does it, for him it's not שותפין, shutafin, she was
always under his control. But okay so the groom does not make
for all
נדרים that she ever took, it's just the ones that the father
was annulling. Just that the father, you know, only that time frame.
Like let's just say that the father annulled something, you know, from
or מקיים mekayeim something, you know, in time A and in time
B and in time C she gets married. So the groom just
gets from time B, not time A. What?
Meaning like there could be a lot of נדרים that she took
and the father could have been involved with many of them. He
doesn't get like carte blanche from the day you were born until
now, it's just that.
No, no, no, anyway the whole thing is ביום שמעו. b'yom sham'o.
Anything that happened more than a day ago is a done deal.
No, ביום שמעו. b'yom sham'o.
Anything that happened more than a day ago before the קידושין kiddushin
is a done deal. It was already הוקם, hukam, end of story.
Okay? The only right, like the father's silence or whatever was already
הוקם, hukam, end of story. The only relevance is things that were
done on that day. Okay? Those are things that have not yet
been הוקם, hukam, have still opportunity for הפרה, yes, basically up until
the קידושין.
kiddushin What about those things that happened before but the male parties
heard about it on the day of קידושין kiddushin or after?
Right. So I think, I'll double check and I'm sure we're going
to deal with it as we continue, but I think it's too
late. If it happened last week and the father said, didn't do
anything, was it מקיים or was it מופר? mufar? Right. But he
didn't hear about it. Oh, he didn't hear about it. Right, right,
not the day of, like that's true, not the day she took
the נדר. Anything that was heard
about a day before, you know, the קידושין kiddushin is a done
deal. It's already הוקם hukam or if he was מפר meifer it's
already הופר. hufar. The only relevance to the groom are things that
the father hears about, you know, after, you know, on the day
of or whatever, you know, the קידושין kiddushin, or after they both
hear about. Right, or it could be you're right, could be a
week after the קידושין kiddushin they both hear about it. Right, you
know, but something that was, it did not already have its status
finalized. Anything that was heard about and a day passed or whatever
before the קידושין, the status the groom can
never undo anything the father did. Correct.
Okay, there's one more question that they're talking about this just, so
then whether it's the father hears about it, שמיעת הנדר, shmiat haneder,
and then a week later she
undergoes קידושין and then the next day the father hears about the
old matter, and a week later the groom hears about the old
matter. So whether it's the father did הפרה on the day that
he heard about it, a week later the ארוס arus did הפרה.
Right, so that's a good question and I'm sure we're going to,
I'm pretty positive we're eventually going to get to all of this,
but exactly, the clock runs out different for different people. So again,
it's, you understand the problem in the פסוקים which pushed חז"ל, which
again points out that it is sort of a חידוש even in
their normal way of seeing the world, giving the ארוס arus any
power. Fundamentally she really is in the father's house. And it's going
to open, it creates a new reality and again, they're not equal
powers, equal partners, right, there's a primary partner and a secondary partner
and it's going to lead to a lot of interesting, now that
we've dealt with the פסוקים, we're going to have a lot of
fun הלכתי halachic discussions about how this partnership works. Okay, so this
is the new פרק perek that we have for us.